Guide to the Gwen J. Bymers papers, [ca.1930]-2002.
Bymers, Gwen J. papers, [ca.1930]-2002
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Gwen J. Bymers papers, [ca.1930]-2002.
23-18-1787
Gwen J., Bymers 1915-
4.1 Cubic Feet.
Correspondence, course materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes correspondence, 1960-1976; historical material, ca.1935-1973; and other miscellaneous papers reflecting Bymers' career as a professor of consumer economics.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor emeritus of consumer economics, Cornell University.
Gwen Bymers was born on June 15, 1915. During World War II she joined the Women's Army Corp and after the war, through the GI Bill, obtained her B.A. degree from the University of North Dakota in 1946 and her Ph.D. in economics from U.C.L.A. in 1958. In 1956 Bymers came to Cornell to become an assistant professor in the Dept. of Household Economics and Management. In 1969 she became chair of the newly formed Dept. of Consumer Economics and Public Policy, a position she held for seven years. Gwen Bymers retired in 1977.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes correspondence, 1960-1976; historical material, ca.1935-1973; publications, photographs, and other papers reflecting Bymers' career as a professor of consumer economics and her work in Ghana.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Bymers, Gwen J.,1915-; Bymers, Gwen J.,1915-; Cornell University--Faculty.
Subjects:
Consumers.; Economics.; Ghana--Study and teaching.; College teachers.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence
Boxes 1, 2 and 5
Series II. Department and Course Material
Box 3
Series III. Research and Consumer Education
Box 3
Series IV. Committees, Workshops, and Seminars
Box 4
Series V. Speeches, Talks, and Papers
Box 4
Series VI. Photographs
Box 3, 4 and 5
Series VII. Biographical Material
Box 5
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence concerning letter written to AFA, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence - resumes, 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1989 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1999 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence - sabbatical, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Spring
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence - sabbatical, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence - sabbatical, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence - Sabbatical, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence - sabbatical, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence - Sabbatical, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence - sabbatical, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Fall
  - Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Winter
  - Correspondence, Spring 1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Summer
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, Spring 1976 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1989 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Pan Am field study correspondence, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Department memos, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Memos to Dept. of Consumer Economics and Public Policy, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Memos and documents regarding Babcock Professorship, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous memos, 1970-1979 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous memos, 1970-1979 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Letters from Africa, 1972-09-1973-04 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Finland, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Australia and New Zealand, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence concerning Gwen's PhD at UCLA, 1950-1956 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence from Gwen, 1946-1972 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence to Gwen, 1980; 1995-2002 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Memos, 1970-1979 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Series II. Department and Course Material
  - HEM policy issues, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Consumer Economics and Public Policy - policy issues (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Sale of 1069 Taughannock Blvd. to Cornell, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Certificate of appreciation - Joint Council on Economic Education, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Documents regarding Better Business Bureau, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Documents concerning cooperation between CE an New York Attorney General, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Quality and credit work - correspondence with Osborne from the Federal Reserve Board, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Credit risk material - Sylvia Lane correspondence, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Consumer legislative issues, 1972-1975 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - College reorganization - reports, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - College reorganization - reports, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - College study report - memos, correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - College focus - college name committee minutes, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - HEM 698 - Household Economics and Housing; course work, documents (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - HEM 698 coursework and documents (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - AHEA - accreditation documents for undergraduate programs in home economics, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Department meeting agendas, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Series III. Research and Consumer Education
  - State Project #72 "Financial Position or Vulnerability Status of Consumer Installment Borrowers", 1956-1963 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Field Study Documents (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Study 690 Survey of Consumer Finances, 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Milk Study - Hatch 210, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - CE and PP Field Study, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Research - food marketing practices among O.A.S.I. recipients schedules, 1957-1960 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Research - food marketing practices among O.S.A.I. recipients, correspondence, 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Household Economics and Management, State Project #72, correspondence (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - State Project #72 - correspondence, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Standardization - publications, 1920-1939 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Bad examples of writing, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Consumer education - historical material, 1920-1939 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Consumer education - historical material, 1920-1939 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Consumer education - historical material, 1930-1939 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Consumer education - historical material, 1930-1949 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Consumer education - historical material, 1940-1959 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Extension consumer education - material from Mary Wood, 1970-1979 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Extension consumer education - New York City, 1970-1979 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Extension consumer education guidelines - 4H, 1970-1979 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Series IV. Committees, Workshops, and Seminars
  - Workshop on dissemination of consumer information in the Dept. of Economics and Household Management, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Salzburg seminar - proposal to have seminar on home economics - attempt failed, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Family Economic Concepts Committee, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Family Economic Concepts Committee, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Rationality question and Home Economics and Management Department, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Institute of Life Insurance Steering Committee that led to Williamsburg meeting - correspondence, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - New York State Woman's Council, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - American Council on Consumer Interests - Dallas conference, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - American Home Economics Association - summary of Lake Placid Conference, questions to consider, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Lake Placid Conference, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - NYSHEA meeting - round table discussion, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - NYSHEA questions and answers, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Consumers in common institute, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Business industry education council activities, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - BIE council documents (Business Industry Education), 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Consumer economics convening, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Omicron no involvement, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - The Institute of Life Insurance Seminar, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Annual institute of New York State College of Human Ecology, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Legislative workshop, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Series V. Speeches, Talks, and Papers
  - Idea folder (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Speeches and talks, 1960-1969 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Speeches and talks, 1960-1969 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Speeches and talks, 1960-1969 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Speeches and talks, 1960-1969 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Outline for consumer economics seminar, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Speeches, 1970-1979 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Speeches, 1970-1979 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Speeches and papers, 1970-1979 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Speeches and papers, 1970-1979 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Talks, 1980-1989 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - "Food Marketing Practices of Older Households," "What is Consumer Education?" "New Trends in Consumer Goods Marketing that Affect the Homemaker", 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - "Publications", 1960-1969 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - "The Consumer Movement and Consumer Education in the U.S." (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - "American Council on Consumer Interests", 1970-1979 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - "The Consumer in the Ghanaian Economy" by Florence Sai and Gwen Bymers, never published, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Continued - Ghanaian economy, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Continued - Ghanaian economy, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Continued - Ghanaian economy, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - "The Grooming and Function of the Consumer Affairs Professional" sponsored by Corning Glass Works, 1978-05 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - "Time Commitment and Financial Position of Installment Debtors", 1963 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Time Horizons in Family Spending or A Study of Household Investments", 1968 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - "Consumerism" (1979); "Economic Theory and its Relevance to Home Management and Family Economics" (1968)and "Statement" (1974), 1968-1979 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "Consumer Economics at Cornell: A Chronicle", 1979 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Series VI. Photographs
  - "Walk by Wood" ladies-Gwen Bymers, Katy Walker, Mary Wood (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Photos taken at Kendal, 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Series VII. Biographical Material
  - High school graduation program, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Job offer telegram, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Trip itinerary, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Academic course work; song from retirement party; funeral program, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Articles about Gwen, 1967-1975 (Box 5, Folder 2)